The last type of error we will cover occurs
when one tries to run code; hence, this type
of error is called a runtime error.
Runtime errors are not syntax errors, nor
are they logic errors.
They are the type of errors that occur when
one tries to do with an app what cannot be
done as the app’s code is being run.
Runtime errors can also stem from logic errors.
It’s essential to distinguish among them.
Syntax errors trigger a “SyntaxError”
message.
Logic errors don't produce any immediate error
messages but may lead to runtime errors.
Runtime errors generate various Python error
codes.
Additionally, runtime errors can sometimes
be mitigated through proper error-handling
techniques that we will cover in the next
set of topics.
One such example of a runtime error is in
this 513-runtime file.
There are no syntax errors that I can see,
and logically, all we are trying to do is
retrieve, on lines 2 and 3, the first and
third items on this list of plant types that
could be covered in a biology class.
Can you spot the potential runtime error here?
Let’s run this code.
We see a fairly common runtime error telling
us that for plant type 3, the list index is
out of range.
What does that mean?
Let’s go back and look at the code.
We have three plant types on line 1, but remember
that when referring to list items, the list
is zero-based, meaning that the first item
is item zero, the second item is item 1, and
so forth.
Thus, getting the item index of three is trying
to get an item that is out of the range of
this list, hence the list index out of range
error.
Another point to make about the error is that
we see a Traceback indicator, which is an
error report showing where the problem occurred.
In this case, the problem is on line 3 in
the code.
To fix this problem and get the correct two
plant items to display, we need to change
the index numbers on lines 2 and 3 to 0 and
2, respectively.
I will make the change and rerun the code,
and the code now works with no runtime errors.
The takeaway here is that the emphasis on
learning runtime errors is understanding what
each runtime error means and knowing how to
read a traceback to see what line number has
code that is causing the runtime error to
occur.
Understanding what a runtime error means can
lead to less time troubleshooting, which leaves
more time to do more fun things, like developing
more apps.
Now that we have covered the three types of
errors, let’s use this knowledge to analyze
and then fix a code example.
This file, 513-analyze, replicates a code
example we worked on elsewhere in the course.
Use the Review 5.1 workbook project to answer
questions and perform possible fixes related
to this file.
I will have the answers for you in the next
video.